Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is ס"ח Samekh Chet
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 68, and we are a good deal ahead
on ס"ח Samekh Chet עמוד ב', Amud Bet, where eight lines from
the top, הני תלתא בבי דקתני למה לי, Hani telasa bavei dekattani
lamma li, and we have just been looking at the debate of
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir about נותן טעם
לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam when it gets a bad taste. רבי שמעון,
Rebbi Shimon, our משנה mishnah says that נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am
lifgam is מותר mutter to the thing. That's why we have a
lot of leniencies, especially when you use something that's more than a
day old, כיון דהוה keivan d'haivah more than a day old. רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir says that נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam is
forbidden, and we are debating the parameters of their debate. And we
just established based on a ברייתא, braisa, supporting עולא's Ulla position, that
they are debating a case of פגם מעיקרא pagum me'ikara when the
very, when initially it gave a bad taste. That's the case where
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's permissible and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says it's forbidden. Even that's forbidden. But if it was השביח ולבסוף
פגם, hishbiach u-levasof pagam, initially its taste was good and then it
turned bad, then everybody would agree that it's forbidden. Once it initially
was good, it creates the forbidden status of the food. And that
fits into what we were saying earlier also in interpreting the משנה
mishnah that if the vinegar falls on the lentils and it's cold,
and then it's heated up, since initially it's good and only after
comes bad, then it remains forbidden. Okay, and we had proved that
based on a whole ברייתא braisa that dealt with different sections relating
to שאור se'or of חולין chullin and of תרומה terumah that fell
in, and also the case of wine and vinegar, forbidden wine and
vinegar that fell on various food items. So now the גמרא Gemara
wants to understand why we needed all sections of that ברייתא. braisa.
So let's take a look. Again, eight lines from the top of
ס"ח Samekh Chet עמוד ב', Amud Bet, middle of the line, הני
תלתא בבי דקתני למה לי? Hani telasa bavei dekattani lamma li? Why
did you need all three sections of the ברייתא? braisa? First the
section dealing with yeast, and then two sections dealing with yeast, and
then a final section dealing with the wine and vinegar that fell
on the lentils. בשלמא בבא דסיפא קא משמע לן בפגם מעיקרא מחלוקת.
Bishlama bava de-seifa kamash lan be-pagum me'ikara machlokes. So the last section,
when the wine fell on the lentils and we sort of demonstrated
yesterday that that was talking about when it initially gave a bad
taste. So that's important. That shows that the debate of רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is when it starts off
with a bad taste. That even there רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
that it is forbidden. ומציעתא נמי השביח ולבסוף פגם דברי הכל אסור.
U-metzi'ata nami hishbiach u-levasof pagam divrei hakol assur.
And the middle case, and here what we're referring to is the
case where first the שאור se'or of תרומה terumah falls in, and
therefore that's actually doing something good when the yeast falls into the
dough. So it makes it forbidden. And then even if afterwards the
additional yeast falls in and it turns it all bad because now
it has, it's overly yeasted. That was the case where רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon said it was forbidden. So that proves that even רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon would agree in a case of השביח hishbiach initially
it's good ולבסוף פגם. u-levasof pagam. So you put those two together
and you have the whole story. פגם מעיקרא Pagum me'ikara is where
they debate and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's okay, and השביח
ולבסוף פגם, hishbiach u-levasof pagam, when the תרומה terumah yeast fell in
and then additional yeast was added, even רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
it's forbidden, there everybody says it's forbidden. Now you have the whole
scope. So why do you need any other part of this ברייתא?
braisa? אלא רישא למה לי? Ella reisha lamma li? Why do you
need the first section, which is where both תרומה terumah yeast and
חולין chullin yeast fell in at the same time? So from the
very beginning there was too much yeast. So that's just another case
of פגם מעיקרא. pagum me'ikara. So why do you need to tell
me that? אלא רישא למה לי? Ella reisha lamma li? השתא מה
סיפא דלא קא משבח כלל אסרי רבנן. Hashta mah seifa dela ka
meshabbach kelal asrei rabbanan. In the case,
on the one hand that's a case of פגם מעיקרא, pagum me'ikara,
yes. But what it also is is as we've been discussing, because
it's yeast it also does improve it. Even though an over-yeasted dough
might not be good for making bread, it's good for sourdough. So
there's an element which makes it better. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so why do you need to tell me about a case
of פגם מעיקרא pagum me'ikara where there's an additional benefit that it's
also now has a positive that it could be used as sourdough?
Why do you need to tell me that? ומה סיפא למה לי
השתא מה סיפא דלא קא משבח כלל אסרי רבנן רישא דקא משבח
מיבעיא? U-mah seifa lamma li? Hashta mah seifa dela ka meshabbach kelal
asrei rabbanan, reisha deka meshabbach mibaya? If רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir in
the end with the vinegar on the
lentils where it's פגם מעיקרא pagum me'ikara and it's only bad, and
even in a case where it's only bad, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says that it's going to be forbidden. השתא מה סיפא דלא קא
משבח כלל אסרי רבנן רישא דקא משבח מיבעיא? Hashta mah seifa dela
ka meshabbach kelal asrei rabbanan, reisha deka meshabbach mibaya? So of course
in a case where it's the too much sourdough where yes, it's
bad because it's too much yeast,
but there's also... a benefit to it. Of course רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir would say it's forbidden. So if by the case of the
of the of vinegar and the lentils, you know that רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says it's forbidden even that when it's bad to begin
with. And from the middle case of the two stages of the
yeast, you know that they agree when it starts off good, why
do you need to tell me another debate about too much yeast
at the beginning that they debate there as well, of course רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir is going to say that case is forbidden. And
it seems as also of course רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say
that it's permissible.
So because it's just a case of bad from the beginning. So
why do you need to tell me that case? So the גמרא
Gemara let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רישא אמר אביי רישא
לרבי שמעון איצטריך. Reisha amar Abaye reisha le'Rebbi Shimon itztreech. Okay,
the רישא reisha is needed for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, yes, maybe
it's not so obvious that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say that
that case is okay. Yes it's bad from the beginning, but as
we also mentioned, there's a good part, it's giving additional yeast to
make it into good sourdough. So and let's see how אביי Abaye
explains why you need a חידוש chiddush for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon,
okay. והכי קאמר ליה רבנן לרבי שמעון. Vehachi ka'amar leh rabbanan le'Rebbi
Shimon. This is what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would be saying to
רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. עיסה זו ראויה להחמיץ בשתי שעות מי גרם
לה שתחמיץ בשעה אחת איסור. Issa zu reuyah lehachmitz b'shtei sha'os mi
garam lah shetachmitz b'sha'ah achas issur.
So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would be saying to רבי שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon, look, I know you פסקן pasken נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am
lifgam is forbidden, is permissible, excuse me. But you should concede in
this case of too much yeast, maybe this case of too much
yeast is a case of essentially a type of a נותן טעם
לשבח. nosein ta'am l'shvach. Why is it a type of a נותן
טעם לשבח? nosein ta'am l'shvach? A, you could say because it makes
good sourdough, but actually אביי Abaye now is framing it a little
bit differently. He's saying because actually initially the effect of the yeast
is that it speeds up the fermentation. The dough rises sooner. The
negative effect comes later, but the positive effect comes first. And therefore
it should be a case of השביח ולבסוף פגם. hisvbeach ulevasof pagam.
So maybe that's why you had to tell me that case of
yeast because there's a reason to think that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
would say it's forbidden. והכי, Vehachi, okay, מי גרם לה שתחמיץ בשעה
אחת איסור. mi garam lah shetachmitz b'sha'ah achas issur. רבי שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would answer back, כשהשביחו שניהם השביחו כשהפגימו
שניהם הפגימו. keshepigchu sheneihem hipigchu keshepagmu sheneihem pagmu.
When it made it better, both of them made it better. Yes,
there was an element of השביח hisvbeach from the beginning, but even
though there was an element of השביח hisvbeach from the beginning, it
wasn't that the איסור issur was doing the השביח hashbeach all by
itself. The איסור issur was only doing the השביח hashbeach in combination
with the היתר. hetter. So you can't actually frame it as השביח
ולבסוף פגם. hisvbeach ulevasof pagam.
Because the איסור issur did
not make it better from the beginning, the איסור issur all by
itself. And therefore that was not enough to give it that status
of איסור, issur, and therefore when it becomes פגם pagam later, it
will be considered נפגם. nifgam. Okay, now I have to say that
that's not a very clear answer. My answer would have been like
that an over-yeasted thing from the very beginning there's too much yeast
in it. Yes it's happening quicker, but it's never actually good, it
always has too much yeast and it's always going to be a
problem. But if רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon here according to the way
the גמרא Gemara seems to be framing it is sort of conceding
that there's two stages, first השביח hisvbeach and ולבסוף ulevasof it's נפגם,
nifgam, then even though it didn't make it השביח hisvbeach all by
itself, if you would have stopped the clock at that moment, you
would have said the איסור issur made the thing better. Who says
it has to make it better all by itself, it still made
it better. And why shouldn't it have a status of being an
אסור, assur, of איסור. issur. So I'm not really totally clear on
how this answer, the way it's being framed that it's first good
and then it becomes bad, how you get out of that, why
is that not השביח ולבסוף פגם. hisvbeach ulevasof pagam. Even if it
didn't do it all by itself, it still was a period in
which the addition of the תרומה terumah only made the yeast better,
at least the way the גמרא's Gemara framing it. רש"י Rashi doesn't
really help here. רש"י Rashi says שניהם השביחו ולא האיסור לבדו השביחו.
she'one hispichu velo ha'issur levado hispicho.
So what? The thing still had a good taste to begin with
and therefore it should have been אסור. assur. I think you really
have to say that even from the outset, the additional yeast was
not all good, it was a mixture of good and bad. All
right, anyway that's why we had to say all three cases, but
at the end of the day, the debate is פגם מעיקרא pagam
mei'ikara and we פסקן pasken that that is okay, but השביח ולבסוף
פגם hisvbeach ulevasof pagam is no good. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, רבי שמעון ליצטרוף היתר ואיסור בהדי הדדי וליצר.
Rebbi Shimon litzterof hetter ve'issur bahadei hadadi v'litza. So the גמרא Gemara
says one
minute, okay, if why can't you according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
why can't you say
exactly this point, that if they both of them were משביח, mashbeach,
okay, so both of them were משביח, mashbeach, that should qualify as
משביח mashbeach again. If we're going to frame this like אביי, Abaye,
that first the additional yeast was make it better and only later
it made it worse. Okay, for רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, so the
גמרא Gemara says רבי שמעון לטעמיה דאמר אפילו איסור ואיסור לא מצטרפי.
Rebbe Shimon letameih de'amar afilu issur ve'issur lo mitstarfe.
No,
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon goes according to his reasoning that he says
even if you have two things of איסור, issur, if each one
doesn't have enough to do it by itself, then it cannot make
something forbidden. What is the רבי שמעון? Rebbe Shimon? Let's take a
look. דתנן הערלה וכלאי הכרם מצטרפין רבי שמעון אומר אין מצטרפין. detnan
ha'orlah vekhilai hakerem mitstarfin Rebbe Shimon omer ein mitstarfin.
So let's say you have, you know,
some grapevine that is within the first three years, so it's ערלה,
orlah, and you have a half of a כזית kezayit of that.
And then you have some grape that was made together with the
wheat and it's כלאי הכרם, kilai hakerem, and you have half a
כזית kezayit of that. And you put those two half כזיתים kezaytim
of grapes into a, you know, a vat of a stew that
has sixty כזיתים... kezaytim... 50, you know, 59 כזיתים. kezaytim. So is
it בטל batel or not?
So the תנא קמא tanna kamma says it's not בטל batel because
you have a full כזית kezayit of אסור assur grapes. אסור assur
for different reasons, but it's a full כזית kezayit of אסור assur
grapes and you need sixty כזיתים, kezaytim, and you don't have sixty
כזיתים, kezaytim, so actually the stuff has the taste of forbidden grapes
even though two different איסורין issurin in it, and it's forbidden. And
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says no, each one operates on its own,
and each grape is בטל batel by itself. Okay, and therefore so
he says you don't combine there, so here too you would not
combine, you know, the איסור issur yeast and the היתר heter yeast
to say that it has the effect of being משביח. mashbiach. Again,
I have to be honest, I do not understand it. It's one
thing to say that you don't combine to say that now, you
know, you have a full כזית kezayit that needs ביטול bittel because
each one is a separate איסור, issur, so each one needs its
own ביטול. bittel. Here the question is when the תרומה terumah yeast
fell in, was it making a positive contribution or a negative contribution?
So, you know, it was making a positive... the way it's being
framed that the negative only happens after the fermenting happens and it
continues to ferment more, I still don't understand why you don't stop
the clock and say right... even if you took out the היתר
heter חולין, chullin, you know, you would still have... even if you
took out the חולין, chullin, the תרומה terumah would still have made
a positive contribution. So not clear to me why we have managed
to solve the השביח ולבסוף פגם hishbiach u-levasof pagam question here. By
the way, worth noting that תוספות Tosfos asks another... you know, conceptually
you're inclined to frame this a different way. Not a way of
צירוף, tziruf, let them combine, but a way of זה וזה גורם.
zeh ve-zeh gorem. What happens when you have two contributing factors? Do
you say since each one is doing a part, it's significant? Or
since, you know, one is not doing it by itself, it's not?
So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says לרבי
שמעון לצרפו היתר לאיסור. le-Rebbe Shimon letsarfo heter le-issur. תוספות Tosfos says
ואם תאמר אמאי לא תלי פלוגתייהו בזה וזה גורם כי דסוף פרק
כל הצלמים. ve-im tomar amai lo tali plugtaiyhu be-zeh ve-zeh gorem ki
desof perek kol hatzlamim. Why not say it's a question of this
one contributes and that one contributes? Why are you framing it as
being מצטרף mitstaref and not זה וזה גורם? zeh ve-zeh gorem? And
now he has an important distinction. ויש לומר דהיינו דוקא שאין בזה
כדי להחמיץ ולא בזה כדי להחמיץ כי מצטרפי הוי ליה זה וזה
גורם. ve-yesh lomar de-hainu davka she-ein be-zeh kedei lehachmitz velo be-zeh kedei
lehachmitz ki mitstarfei havei leih zeh ve-zeh gorem. Normally when you say
this and this contributes is when each one doesn't do it enough,
each one is necessary but not sufficient. And therefore the point is
when you have two things that are both operating together, you know,
do you look at them as on the one hand you could
say no one of them does enough, so it's not meaningful. On
the other hand, you could sort of see them in partnership and
it דווקא davka is meaningful. That's the question of
זה וזה גורם. zeh ve-zeh gorem. אבל כשיש בכל אחד כדי להחמיץ
אין שייך זה וזה גורם ואפילו למאן דשרי התם אסור הכא. aval
keshe-yesh bekhol echad kedei lehachmitz ein shayach zeh ve-zeh gorem ve-afilu leman
desharei hatam assur hacha. Now you... now תוספות Tosfos says here, you
could have said both ways. You could say when they both are
needed they're both operating together, that's also a type of a question
about like שנים שעשוהו, shnayim she-asuhu, when two people combine to do
a מלאכה melachah on שבת. Shabbos. But תוספות Tosfos has said here,
no, that when... that when each one is sufficient by itself, there's
more of a reason to say איסור, issur, right? If each one
is insufficient then you could say well then the איסור issur is
not really doing everything by itself. Here each one is sufficient, you
could have taken out the other and either one would have done
it, so that's a stronger reason to say that the איסור issur
should be a problem. Okay, but we're not going to frame it
as זה וזה גורם, zeh ve-zeh gorem, we're going to frame it
as צירוף. tziruf. But again, I have to say I don't understand
at all the comparison to the case of ערלה וכלאי הכרם orlah
ve-khilai hakerem and you know why we're not just framing this as
שבח shevach and then the פגם pegam comes later. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ההוא עכברא דנפל לחביתא דשיכרא. hahu akhbra denafal le-chavita de-shikhra. A
rat fell into a bottle of beer or mead or
whatever, and somehow it... for taste transferred. תוספות Tosfos asks why did
the taste transfer? It's all cold. So maybe says it stayed in
there a long time and eventually the taste seeped out, that's a
whole question that the ראשונים Rishonim deal with about כבוש כמבושל, kavush
kemevushal, can you keep something in a liquid long enough that even
in cold taste will transfer? Or who knows, maybe it fell into
the beer when it was boiling or something when it was being
processed. Okay, but the rat fell into the beer. אמרו רבנן קמיה
דרב ששת, Amru rabbanan kamei d'Rav Sheshes, so the rabbis said
to רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, נימא קסבר, neima kasavar, sorry, I skipped
a line. אסר רב לההוא שיכרא. Assar Rav lahu shichra. רב Rav
said okay, the beer is forbidden. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב ששת, Amru
rabbanan kamei d'Rav Sheshes, so the rabbis said it to רב ששת.
Rav Sheshes. נימא קסבר, Neima kasavar, let's say רב Rav who said
it's forbidden, why is it forbidden? I mean, it's disgusting, it's a
rat. נימא קסבר נותן טעם לפגם אסור? Neima kasavar nosein taam lifgam
assur? Does רב Rav hold that נותן טעם לפגם nosein taam lifgam
is forbidden? Right? That goes back to the debate of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So is he really going
to פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? אמר להו רב ששת,
Amar lehu Rav Sheshes, רב ששת Rav Sheshes said back to them,
בעלמא סבר רב נותן טעם לפגם מותר. Be'alma savar Rav nosein taam
lifgam mutar. No, no, no. רב Rav holds נותן טעם nosein taam
as a general rule is מותר. mutar. והכא חידוש הוא, Vecha chiddush
hu, here
when it comes to the rat, it's a חידוש. chiddush. דמימיס מאיס
ובדילי אינש מיניה. Damimas ma'is uvdili inish minei.
Rats are disgusting and people normally don't eat rats. Okay. ואפילו הכי
אסריה רחמנא. Ve'afilu hachi asrei rachmana.
And nevertheless the Torah forbids it, forbade rats. הילכך נותן טעם לפגם
נמי אסור. Hilkach nosein taam lifgam nami assur. Therefore נותן טעם לפגם
nosein taam lifgam should also be forbidden. So what does this mean?
So I'm not going to say רש"י's Rashi's explanation which is a
little difficult, I'll say תוספות Tosfos which is the general way the
ראשונים Rishonim understand it. They say look, normally, you know, the Torah
forbids things that taste good, and therefore we can say that therefore
when they taste bad, that's a status of נותן טעם לפגם nosein
taam lifgam and it's permissible. But if the Torah here, excuse me,
and it's permissible. But if the Torah here is saying rats are
forbidden even though they're disgusting, then what the Torah is basically saying
is we don't care about the taste. This thing is forbidden regardless
of all considerations of taste. This works particularly good if you think
that a rat is really under normal circumstances inedible. So then it
is sort of saying that like, you know, even though it's inedible,
it's still forbidden just to put it into your mouth. Okay. If
that's true about the בעין be'en of the rat, then the נותן
טעם לפגם, nosein taam lifgam, even though it's a disgusting taste, when
it comes to rats, the Torah is not looking through that lens,
that normal lens, and it's going to be forbidden regardless. Okay, that's
a reasonable argument. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with
this. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב ששת, Amru lei rabbanan leRav Sheshes, אלא
מעתה, ela mei'ata, if that's true that you sort of say this
whole thing is a חידוש, chiddush, you know, it's disgusting and like
nevertheless it's forbidden. אלא מעתה, Ela mei'ata, ליטמא לח ויבש? letamei lach
veyavesh? Why not say that a rat should also be טמא tamei
even if it is dried out and desiccated? And okay, so first
let's see why how we know that's not true, but then we'll
try to understand what the logic there is of the connection of
those two. אלמה תנן, Alama tnan, why do we teach in a
משנה Mishna מטמאין לחים ואין מטמאין יבשים? metamin lachin ve'ein metamin yeveshin?
That, you know, the שרצים sheratzim are טמא tamei לח, lach, but
they're not when they're still moist but not when they are dried
out. So
now what's the logic of the question? So תוספות Tosfos says the
logic is somewhat similar, that if you're saying that we're not going
to look at it through normal standards of fit to be eaten,
fit to be tasted, those types of things are not relevant, this
thing is just totally forbidden, you know, then the same should be
true in terms of issues of טומאה. tumah. Even if it's desiccated
and normally you would say it's not the thing itself, okay, but
once we're not concerned with normal measures of thing that the thing
qualifies as food, doesn't matter if it's inedible, it's still forbidden, then
maybe also desiccated it shouldn't matter. All right, it's not still not
totally clear what exactly the question is, but all right.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מאי, ela mai, so the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא מעתה אלמה מטמאין לחים ואין מטמאין יבשים? ela mei'ata
alama metamin lachin ve'ein metamin yeveshin? אמרת ליה למימר, Amaih lach lemeimar,
שכבת זרע אמר רחמנא בראויה להזריע? shichvas zera amar rachmana bera'uya lehazria?
והכא נמי, Hacha nami, sorry, I skipped the line again. Okay, מטמאין
לחים ואין מטמאין יבשים. metamin lachin ve'ein metamin yeveshin. לטעמיך, Letameich, so
רב ששת Rav Sheshes says back to them, שכבת זרע תטמא לח
ויבש? shichvas zera tetamei lach veyavesh? According to you, that when things
are like disgusting and they're not in the category of food and
so on, the טומאה tumah should be even when they're dried out?
So say that also about semen. You know, that's obviously not in
the category of food and so let's say also that that should
be even when it's dried out. אלמה תנן, Alama tnan, why do
we teach in a משנה Mishna מטמאין לחים ואין מטמאין יבשים? metamin
lachin ve'ein metamin yeveshin? That even when it comes to semen as
well, it's only moist and not dry. אלא מאי אית לך למימר
Ela mai it lach lemeimar by semen? שכבת זרע
אמר רחמנא בראויה להזריע. Shichvas zera amar rachmana bera'uya lehazria. It says
שכבת זרע, shichvas zera, seed, the laying of seed, which means when
it is, you know, fit to, it's in a state where it
could actually lead to conception, בראויה להזריע. berauya lehazria.
והכא נמי, Hacha nami, במותם אמר רחמנא כעין מותם. bemosem amar rachmana
k'ein mosem. So when it says, you know, if you touch them
in their death, it means when they're in a state like when
they died. So the תורה Torah here says yes, it has
to
be. and not really edible or doesn't taste good, maybe it remains
forbidden even though נותן טעם לפגם. nosein ta'am lifgam. Okay, so that's
a pretty good argument.
So מתיב ליה רב שימי מנהרדעא maskiv lei Rav Shimi mi-Nahardea asks,
ומי מאיס? u-mi ma'is? Wait a minute, I challenge your assertion that
rats are disgusting. והלא עולה על שולחן מלכים. ve-halo olah al shulchan
melachim. You can have, you know, some places you can have rats
go on be served in front of kings. It's a delicacy! Who
says it's disgusting? Just because you get, you know, sort of recoiled
from it, you know, you find it repugnant, have you ever tasted
it? Who says it tastes bad? So אמר רב שימי מנהרדעא, amar
Rav Shimi mi-Nahardea, לא קשיא. lo kashya. No, no, no, it's true,
but you gotta understand there are two different types of rats. הא
בדברא הא
בדמתא. ha bid-davra ha bid-masa. Are we talking about a rat of
the field or are we talking one in the city? So if
you look at what רש"י Rashi says, דמתא, demasa, so, you know,
in the city is disgusting, also goes through the sewers or whatever.
Anyway, but עכברא דדברא, achbara de-davra, רש"י Rashi says, אשקורול asqurul בלא"ז,
be-la'az, so it's a squirrel. Okay? So it might be that it
depends what you're talking about. All right, so there we have these
opinions about, about,
but it might be some rats that actually are, do taste good,
but we still don't know the story if rats are forbidden even
if they're disgusting, what's the story with their taste? So now the
גמרא's Gemara going to sort of conclude about this.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, הילכתא נותן טעם לפגם מותר.
hilchesa nosein ta'am lifgam mutar. הילכתא Hilchesa is נותן טעם לפגם nosein
ta'am lifgam is מותר, mutar, which is a good thing for us
for as practical
הלכה. halakha. ועכברא בשיכרא, Ve-achbara be-shichra, and the case about a rat
in the, in the beer or the mead, לא ידנא מאי טעמא
דרב. lo yadana mai ta'ama de-Rav. At the end I don't know
the reason of רב. Rav. אי משום דקסבר נותן טעם לפגם אסור
ולא עבדינן כוותיה. ei mishum de-kasvar nosein ta'am lifgam assur ve-lo avidnan
kevaseih. Maybe he holds נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam is אסור
assur and we don't rule like him, not like we were saying
before, maybe he genuinely does hold נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam
is אסור. assur. אי משום דקסבר נותן טעם לפגם מותר ועכברא בשיכרא
אשבוחי משבח, ei mishum de-kasvar nosein ta'am lifgam mutar ve-achbara be-shichra asvuchi
meshvach, or maybe he holds נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam is
מותר mutar and ועכברא בשיכרא אשבוחי משבח, ve-achbara be-shichra asvuchi meshvach, and
maybe he thinks that a rat in beer actually makes it taste
better. So what's interesting about רבא Rava is he's completely rejecting this
idea that bad-tasting food, נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam wouldn't apply,
מותר mutar wouldn't apply. No, even if a rat tastes disgusting, the
principles of נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam still apply. Okay, we
can discuss that in a minute. But the reason he might have
said it might be better is he might have felt that a
rat actually made the beer better, which would be strange. You know,
תוספות Tosafot says maybe did it make it taste better, but maybe
it made it more pungent or more, I don't know, something did
it strengthen it in some way. Okay, but what's important is that
the principle is that even if it is a bad-tasting thing like
a, like, you know, naturally bad-tasting like the rat, it seems like
we're prepared to say נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam is still
going to be מותר. mutar. So there two points about this before
we sort of move on. One is that, what's the logic of
that? I mean, it's good logic. If it's disgusting even when it
tastes bad, shouldn't it even be disgusting if it gives, you know,
shouldn't נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam still be, if it's אסור
assur even when it tastes disgusting, shouldn't נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am
lifgam also be אסור? assur? So here the ראשונים Rishonim basically say
the following: they say
that, they say that,
that there's a difference between בעין be-ayin and טעם. ta'am. You know,
when you eat the actual thing itself, then it's as long as
it's edible, it doesn't matter if it tastes bad. You're still eating
the actual rat and the תורה Torah forbids you to eat the
rat. But when it comes to the taste, the תורה Torah forbids
you to eat the, to eat something that is called טעם. ta'am.
And you know, and that's why we learn out from נבילה neveilah
that טעם לפגם ta'am lifgam is מותר. mutar. Bad taste, even if
it's not inedible, even if it's just bad taste, bad taste is
not הלכתית halachically טעם. ta'am. When it comes to something being food,
if it's inedible, it's not food. When it comes to something being
taste, טעם, ta'am, the forbidden טעם, ta'am, then if something is not
normally desired to be tasted, bad taste is not הלכתית halachically טעם.
ta'am. So even though the thing itself tastes bad and is forbidden,
the טעם לפגם ta'am lifgam is מותר mutar because that doesn't constitute
taste and the תורה Torah only forbids taste. It forbids the בעין,
be-ayin, the בעין be-ayin you're eating, but as taste that's not taste.
So that seems to be the reason for that. The other thing
that's worth mentioning
is also that
is also that this idea that something is disgusting. Is it disgusting
in taste or is it disgusting because you sort of recoil from
it? And the פסק בהלכה psak be-halacha is is that like you
know, if a cockroach let's say falls into your, you know, into
your,
what do you call it? Your scrambled eggs, you know, then it's
נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam and it's מותר. mutar. Even though,
even though נותן טעם לפגם nosein ta'am lifgam and it's מותר, mutar,
even though
the,
you know, who knows how a cockroach tastes? Maybe a cockroach tastes
good. good, but the fact that you find it disgusting and repugnant
or whatever and that's how you're going to be thinking about the
food, that also sort of qualifies in terms of these issues of
נותן טעם לפגם. nosen ta'am lifgam.
Okay, so let's continue now to the next part. איבעיא להו, Iba'i
lehu,
last two lines on ס"ח ע"ב, Samech-Ches Amud Beis, they asked the
following question. איב Iba top of ס"ט ע"א, Samech-Tes Amud Aleph, נפלו
לגו חלא
מאי?
Nafalo l'go
chala mai? Let's say this, you know, this rat fell into not
beer but fell into vinegar. Okay? So if you look at Rashi,
what's the question? מי אמרינן החומץ טעמו קשה ואין השרץ מפיגו לתת
בו טעם? Mi aminan hachometz ta'amo kasheh v'ein hasheretz mafigo liteit bo
ta'am? Maybe the vinegar is so pungent that it won't give any
taste. מאי? Mai? So אמר ליה רב הילל לרב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Hillel l'Rav Ashi, הוי עובדא בי רב כהנא ואסר רב כהנא.
Havay uvda bei Rav Kahana v'asar Rav Kahana. There's a story, a
case in the case of Rav Kahana and he forbade it. Now,
is it the fact that it didn't give bad taste but it
gave good taste, or it gave no
taste? You know, not exactly clear. As Rashi says, because it didn't
give taste, it's מותר. muttar. But if it gave taste, even bad
taste, it would be forbidden because נותן טעם לפגם nosen ta'am lifgam
is אסור. assur. Not exactly clear what the various possibilities are, but
let's somehow there's an assumed that it would neutralize the bad taste
and the taste it would give would be positive or neutral and
presumably neutral taste would also be a problem. Okay. אמר ליה ההוא,
Amar lei ha'u, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so the answer came
back. So that's what, so that Rav Hillel tried to bring a
proof to Rav Ashi from the Rav Kahana story, and אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said back to him: No, ההוא אימרותי אימרתי. Ha'u
imrutay imratay. No, no, no, there little pieces of the rat got
like left into the actual vinegar and it was a problem of
בעין, be'ein, not a problem of taste. Interesting point, this leads Tosafot
to ask, to say: How do we eat honey since our honey
has little bees' legs in it? Little pieces of בעין. be'ein. So
it doesn't matter if it's טעם לפגם, ta'am lifgam, you're eating the
actual בעין. be'ein. And that leads Tosafot to take a look, you
know, Tosafot says ההוא אימרותי אימרתי, ha'u imrutay imratay, יש לי תמוה
עכשיו היאך אנו אוכלים דבש דבורים.
Yeish li tmi'ah achshav heichan
anu ochlim dvas dvorim.
How do we eat bee honey? As opposed to, you know, date
honey, which is the דבש dvas of the Torah. ולא רגלי דבורים
מעורבים בדבש? V'lo raglei dvorim me'uravim badvash? Don't you have the legs
of the bees? ואף על גב דהוי פגם מכל מקום השרץ עצמו
דאיתא מיהא אסור לכולי עלמא. V'af al gav d'havay pgam mikol makom
hasheretz atzmo d'ita miha assur l'chuli alma. But it's the בעין, be'ein,
נותן טעם לפגם nosen ta'am lifgam doesn't matter. So he says, ולכן
נראה לרבינו תם דהנך רגלי דבורים כיון דעצמות בעלמא נינהו מותרין. V'lachen
nireh l'Rabbeinu Tam d'hanech raglei dvorim kivan d'atzmot b'alma ninhu mutarin. He
says, they're only bones, there's no meat on them, and therefore the
bones of a forbidden animal are not forbidden if there's no meat.
So we can worry about whether that's actually true or not, but
it's fascinating dealing with the reality that they ate honey and then
they had to try to have a justify how. Okay, let's try
to, let's finish up here to the Mishnah. Okay. רבינא סבר לשעורי
במאה וחד. Ravina savar l'shiuarei b'meah v'chad.
Ravina thought that, you know, when it came to this rat in
the beer, you would go by a hundred and one. It would
be בטל, batel, but you would need more. So that's fascinating. Right
now we're even assuming that it's going to be more problematic than
normal איסורים. issurim. I mean Tosafot tries to figure this out, like
saying like maybe on the one hand it's a bad taste, on
the other hand it increases the pungency of the vinegar, so you
know, it might be that it requires less than normal, might be
it's טעם לפגם, ta'am lifgam, it might be that it requires more
than normal. So this is an opinion that you need a hundred
and one. Okay, and it's no worse than תרומה, truma, דתנן תרומה
עולה באחד ומאה. d'tnan truma olah b'echad u'meah. If you have a
hundred and one against תרומה truma it's permissible, so therefore even if
we're going to be stricter here, a hundred and one should be
enough. אמר ליה רב תחליפא בר גיזלא לרבינא דילמא כתבלין של תרומה
דקדירה דמי ולא בטיל טעמיהו. Amar lei Rav Tachlipa bar Gizla l'Ravina
dilma k'tavlin shel truma d'kdira dami v'lo batil ta'ameihu. If you're going
to, well,
I don't know, if you're going to look for more stringent types
of models, how about things that are like spices of תרומה truma
or of עשר esser or whatever? That there, that's not בטל batel
because it can be tasted even a small amount. Now Tosafot points
out, and it's important to notice, that sometimes there's this phrase עבידא
לטעמא, avida l'ta'ama, things that are made for taste, spices, you know,
even a small amount can be tasted, it doesn't and it needs
a lot more than sixty. It doesn't mean it's never בטל. batel.
It's not like it's a more strict איסור. issur. It just means
that there's a reality that it gives off a lot of טעם
ta'am even with a tiny amount. So you need much, much more.
You know, you have to figure out how much more. A thousand,
two thousand, eventually it's בטל. batel. Okay anyway, so if you're looking
for a strict model, there are stricter models. רב אחא שיער בחלא
בחמישין. Rav Acha shier b'chala b'chamishin. Rav Acha says when it came
to vinegar fifty is enough. Okay? So that's less than sixty. רב
שמואל בריה דרב איקא שיער בשיכרא בשישין. Rav Shmuel brei d'Rav Ika
shier b'shichra b'shishin. He said that when it came to beer sixty
is enough. But again, you need sixty. We're not just saying טעם
לפגם. ta'am lifgam. So that's also interesting. והלכתא אדידי ואדידי בשישין וכן
כל איסורים שבתורה. V'hilchta adidi v'adidi b'shishin v'chen kol issurim shebaTorah.
And the הלכה halacha is that whether beer or vinegar you need
sixty, and also by all איסורים שבתורה. issurim shebaTorah. You know, getting
back, and that leads Rashi to an interesting discussion about
מין במינו min b'mino is שישין, shishin, but Rashi argues that מין
בשאינו מינו min b'she'eino mino is במשהו. b'mashu. We do not rule
that way, we say מין במינו min b'mino is also בשישין. b'shishin.
But that's a very important ruling here, that the general rule is
שישין. shishin. Again. and one also assumes here that the שישים shishim
maybe we're talking about when it's בעין b'en or in a circumstance
when it's not טעם לפגם. tam lifgam. Well, of course, if any
of this were טעם לפגם, tam lifgam, it would be totally מותר
mutar and as I said, we פסקן pasken even טעם לפגם tam
lifgam by things that have a disgusting taste. Okay, we will end
here.